准备好了吗  孩子们
Are you ready, kids?
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
我听不见
I can't hear you
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
是谁住在深海的大菠萝里
Who lives in a pineapple under the sea?
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
方方黄黄伸缩自如
Absorbent and yellow and porous is he
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
如果四处探险是你的愿望
If nautical nonsense be something you wish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
那就敲敲甲板让大鱼开路
Then drop on the deck and flop like a fish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
准备
Ready
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
失望假期
分镜总监
编剧
翻译: 1440kHz
技术总监
动画总监
制片指导
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
蟹堡王
章鱼哥
Squidward
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
快帮我解脱吧
Just put me out of me misery
为什么  蟹老板
Why, Mr. Krabs?
多美好的一天  哪里会出错呢
What could be wrong on such a fine day?
哪好了
Fine?
今天才不好  小子
Today's not the day for that word, boy
因为我收到了煎炸厨师工会的信
Not after I received this letter
from the fry cooks' union
上面写  煎炸厨师海绵宝宝
It says here: "Fry cook, SpongeBob SquarePants
积攒过多假期未放
has accumulated too much vacation time"
你要是再不休假
And if you don't take some time off
我就会被罚款了
I'll have to pay a fine
休假
Time off?
看来没办法更委婉地说了
I guess there's just no other way to say this
海绵宝宝  放大假
SpongeBob, take a vacation
遵命  蟹老板
Aye, aye, Mr. Krabs
比我想象的还要顺利
Well, that went better than I expected
我准备好了  要放大假
I'm ready, vacation
放大假  放大假
Vacation, vacation
小蜗
Hey, Gary
没错  小蜗
That's right, Gary
我提早回家了
I am home early
我放大假了
I'm on vacation
晚安  小蜗
Well, good night, Gary
放大假
Vacation
海草哥麦片
早安  蟹堡王的员工们
Good morning, Krusty crew
你好  章鱼哥
And hello, Squidward
我还以为你去放大假了
I thought you were on vacation
现在也还在放呢
He was, and is
我不是叫你去放大假了吗  小子
I told you to take a vacation, boy
什么是放大假
What's a vacation?
放大假就是不用来上班
Well, a vacation is when you don't come in to work
不上班
No work
那我整天要干嘛
What will I do all day?
不知道
I don't know--
去玩什么的  反正不关我事
just go, have fun or whatever, I really don't care
总之不能来这
You just can't be here
可我走了  谁来煎肉饼清理烤架
But who will fry the patties
and clean the grill while I'm gone?
章鱼哥自己没办法搞定
Squidward can't do it all alone
我更不去搞
Nor will I
所以我才雇了个
That's why I've hired
无薪实习生来临时帮你代班
an unpaid intern as your temporary replacement
早安  老板
Good morning, boss
我准备好第一天上班了
I'm ready for my first day
说海星
Speaking of starfish
代班到
here's your replacement right here
代班
Replacement?
嗨  海绵宝宝
Hi, SpongeBob
少插科打诨害我赔钱了
That's enough banter on my dime
好的  老板
Okay, boss
等一下  派大星
Wait a second, Patrick
上班得要有正确的工具才行
You'll need the right tools for the job
这挠肚子器上还放了个小小的我
They put a tiny me in this belly-scratcher
竟然还能挠背
It scratches backs, too
接下来交给我吧  海绵宝宝
I'll take it from here, SpongeBob
回家去吧
Just go on home
开开心心放大假
Enjoy your vacation
我真得给派大星示范一下
I really should show Patrick
正确的翻肉饼技巧
the proper patty- flipping technique
我放大假了  小蜗
I'm on vacation, Gary
不能回去上班
I'm not allowed to go to work
我的胃都瘪下去了
My stomach has receded
蟹老板不让我到蟹堡王上班
Mr. Krab said I couldn't work at the Krusty Krab
又没不让我过去吃饭啊
He didn't say I couldn't eat there
这就是我回去的门票
This is my ticket back inside
走开  海绵宝宝
Go away, SpongeBob
你毁了我的假期
You're ruining my vacation--
害我没法远离你
from you
我不是来看你的  章鱼哥
I'm not here to see you, Squidward
海绵宝宝  非得再那样闹一次吗
SpongeBob, do we have to go through this again?
我过来是当客人  不是来上班的
I'm here as a customer, not an employee
只是找派大星买个蟹黄堡当午餐
Just going to grab a Krabby Patty
with Patrick for lunch
好  但是只准吃午餐
All right, but lunch only
要是敢碰一下锅铲
If you so much as touch a spatula
就滚戴维琼斯柜子放大假去吧
you'll be vacationing in Davy Jones's locker
我向你保证
You have my word, sir
不上班
No working
派大星  来吃午餐了
Hey, Pat, it's time for your lunch
派大星
Patrick
不可以那样
You can't do that
要把烤架的温度
You need to turn up the grill
调到整整298华氏度
to exactly 298 degrees Fahrenheit
147.78摄氏度
派大星  不能这样糟蹋蟹黄堡
Patrick, this is no way to treat a Krabby Patty
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
上班的事  我跟你怎么交代的
What did I tell you about working?
等等
Wait
不是你想的那样
It's not what you think
滚出去  小子
Out you go, boy
可我的知识可以帮派大星
But my knowledge could help Patrick
维持蟹堡王的高水准
maintain the high standard of the Krusty Krab
这边的一切我们都能搞定
We've got it all under control here
假没放完  就别让我看到你人影
I don't want to see hide nor tail of you
until your vacation is over
明白没
you got that?
明白  蟹老板
Yes, Mr. Krabs
小子  滚吧
Well, boy, off you go
没放完就别回来
Don't come back until it's over
怎么办
What to do?
我知道有什么能让我振作起来
I know just the thing to get the spirits up
官方正版蟹堡王玩具套装
The official Krusty Krab play set
海绵宝宝  请马上来二十份蟹黄堡
SpongeBob, I need 20 Krabby Patties
on the double, please
没问题  章鱼哥先生
Sure thing, Mr. Squidward, sir
二十份蟹黄堡马上来
20 Krabby Patties coming up
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
你在里面干嘛
What are you doing here?
再不把你方屁股挪回家  我会亏钱的
You're going to cost me some loot
if you don't get your square keister home
滚出去
Out, out, out
放完假再回来
Until your vacation is over
放这无聊的大假能干嘛
What to do on this boring vacation?
我知道有什么能让我振作起来
I know just the thing to get the old spirits up
请来二十份蟹黄堡
I need 20 Krabby Patties, please
没问题  老兄弟老章鱼
Sure thing, old buddy, old squid
二十份蟹黄堡马上
20 Krabby Patties coming
你说得对  小蜗
You're right, Gary
放假老想着蟹堡王  确实不健康
It is unhealthy to think about the Krusty Krab
while I'm on vacation
我得出门走走
I need to get out of the house
蟹老板  他又来了
Mr. Krabs, he's out there again
我来搞定
I'll deal with this
小子  你踏入了蟹堡王的领地了
Boy, you're on Krusty Krab property
退回去
Back it up
入口
远点
Further
行了
That'll do
水母田
蟹老板说得对
Mr. Krabs is right
想开心放假
In order to enjoy my vacation
就得身心都远离工作
I need to stay away from work, physically and mentally
这倒让我想起了
That reminds me of
对
Yeah
给我慢着  工作狂宝宝先生
Hold it right there, Mr. WorkaholicPants
你现在是在放假
You're on vacation
得坐好放松
You need to just sit down and relax
这还差不多
That's more like it
坐好看云
Just sit back and watch the clouds
那朵像水母
That one's a jellyfish
那朵像海盗船
That's a pirate ship
少盐番茄酱
那朵像少盐番茄酱
And that's a low-salt ketchup
少盐番茄酱
Low-salt ketchup?
热腾腾的面包送到了
Got your steaming hot bun delivery here
怎么一回事了
What is the big idea here?
喂
Hello?
Hello
干嘛
Yeah?
喂
Hello
卫生间
我都不知道自己有耳朵
I didn't even know I had an ear
那个我刚清理过的
I just cleaned that one
派大星
Patrick
它会讲话
It talks
救命啊
Somebody help
我被困住了
I'm stuck
蟹老板
Mr. Krabs
感谢海神王  你来了
Thank Neptune, it's you
我有点进退两难
I'm in a bit of a fix here
蟹老板
Mr. Krabs
不要
No
又怎么了
Now what?
我今天受够你了  小子
Had enough for one day, son
谢谢你开船送我回家  蟹老板
Thanks for the ride home, Mr. Krabs
没关系  我的小子
Not a problem at all, me boy
下一个路口右转
Just take the next right
蟹老板  都开过路口了
Mr. Krabs, we just passed the turnoff
我家在后面那个方向  蟹老板
My house is back that way, Mr. K
远了去了  小子
Far out, little man
远了去了
Far out
你刚刚说要带我去哪
Where did you say you were taking me?
小子你看
Look, boy--
我带了你锅铲
I brought your spatula
快啊  小子
Come on, boy
快啊
come on
快拿啊  小子
Now get it, boy
拿啊
Get it
拿锅铲
Get the spatula
去捡
Go get it
开心放大假去吧  小子
Enjoy your vacation, boy
太过分了
It's not fair
蟹老板干嘛要费尽气力赶走我
Why would Mr. Krabs try so hard to get rid of me?
我只是放个假而已
I'm only on vacation
除非
Unless
这个假
it's a
永远放不完
permanent vacation
对了
That's it
蟹老板要找人替代我
Mr. Krabs wants to replace me
早该知道的
I should have known
派大星一直都眼红我的工作
Patrick's had his eye on my job all along
他一直都在密谋
He's been scheming
害别人以为我过时了
They think I'm outdated
害别人以为我完蛋了
They think I'm all washed up
这就见识给别人看
Well, I'll show them
到蟹堡王上班
Working at the Krusty Krab
整天做蟹黄堡
Flipping Krabby Patties all day
做蟹堡王
Flipping Krusty Krab--
上班
working
堡蟹
Patties Krab
这首歌好难记啊
That's a hard song to remember
他们以为自己谁啊
Who do they think they are?
我给蟹堡王奉献了大好年华
I've given the best years of my life to this place
结果蟹堡王的人却想把我当垃圾开除
and they think they can just fire me like that, like trash?
想都别想
I don't think so
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob?
是你吗
Is that you?
我一直在等你呢  派大星
I've been waiting for you, Patrick
海绵宝宝  你吓到我了
SpongeBob, you're scaring me
要点什么
What'll it be?
来份蟹黄堡
One Krabby Patty, please
一份蟹黄堡
One shell on a shingle
好家伙
Well, I'll be
派大星  你的厨艺提升了一千倍
Patrick, you're cooking's improved one-thousandfold
恭喜你  小子
Congratulations, boy
你总算掌握诀窍了
You finally got the hang of it
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob?
怪不得
No wonder
派大星一小时可做不出那么多蟹黄堡
Patrick could never flip that many patties in an hour
那家伙是怎么了
What happened to that feller anyway?
我叫他待家里看电视了
I told him to stay home and watch television
为什么那么做  小子
Why'd you do it, laddy?
蟹老板
Mr. Krabs
我太爱蟹堡王的臭油
I love the putrid grease of the Krusty Krab so much
根本就走不开
I just couldn't stay away
你不用走了
You don't have to
你积攒的假已经放完了
Your accumulated vacation time is used up
工会再也没法罚我款了
The union can't fine me anymore
你一定省下了不少钱吧
You must have saved a fortune
那当然了
Bumping Barnacle, yes
就是这么多
And there she is
比我一年赚到的还多
That's more than I make in a year
别找我加工资
Don't be asking me for a raise
给我回去工作
Just get back to work
万岁
Yippee
我欣然接受
I happily acquiesce
假发潮
分镜总监
编剧
翻译: 1440kHz
技术总监
动画总监
制片指导
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
天啊  这一定会是我们最棒的巡演了
Man, this is going to be our most rocking tour ever
对
Yeah
兄弟们  看我的新造型首次登场
Hey, dudes, check out the debut of my new look
你头上那是什么
What's that on your head?
对啊  那是假发还是一叠厕纸
Yeah, is that a wig or a pile of toilet paper?
真是的  给个机会嘛
Come on, guys, give it a chance
让我试戴一下
Let me try it on
你害我反光的秃头露出来了
You've revealed my shiny dome
烫手山芋
Hot potato
接着
Catch
还给我啊
Give it back, man
想要就去接啊  兄弟
If you want it, you got to catch it, dude
天啊
Oh, man
我漂亮的假发
My beautiful wig
垃圾场
垃圾
假发公墓
裤头村
我准备好了
I'm ready
我准备
I'm read
这是什么
What is this?
卷卷的长发
Curly tresses?
蓬蓬的质感
Poofy texture?
痒痒的头皮
Itchy scalp?
是顶假发
It's a wig
嗨  派大星
Hi, Patrick
你觉得我新造型怎么样
How do you like my new look?
我来救你了
I'll save you
我要救你脱离那个吃脑子的外星人
I'm saving you from that brain-eating alien
它还在袭击你脑袋呢
that's attacking your head
派大星  唯一袭击我的东西就是你
Patrick, the only thing attacking me is you
抱歉
Sorry
没事
It's okay
你干嘛那样
Why did you do that?
还以为你头上戴的是新型棉花糖呢
I thought it was a new type of
cotton candy you wear on your head
不是  不过那点子很有创意
Well, it's not, but that is an excellent idea
那又是什么
Then what is it?
是我的新造型
It's my new look
我戴了顶假发
I'm wearing a wig
假发吗
A wig?
我憋
I can't
我憋不住
I can't stand
天啊
Oh, boy
你不觉得那有点傻吗
Don't you think that's a little silly?
天啊
Oh, man
我每周泡调味澡的时间到了
It's time for my weekly condiment soak
芥末
麻烦回避一下
Do you mind?
假发不错
Nice wig
谢了
Thanks
我今天可时髦了
I am very fashionable today
时髦宝宝
Hey, Square Fashion
时装不错
Nice couture
多谢了
Why, thank you
所以那个
So, that
发型不错  海绵宝宝
Nice 'do, SpongeBob
对
Yeah
可以上哪做呢
Where can I get one?
蟹堡王
那假发跟你也太搭了
That wig really suits you
此处点餐
嗨  章鱼哥
Hi, Squidward
何人何事何地何时何因何法
Who, what, wher, when, why, how?
注意到我今天哪不一样没  章鱼哥
Notice anything different about me today, Squidward?
没
Nope
我戴了顶假发
I'm wearing a wig
还真是
Oh, yeah
我怎么会没注意到呢
How could I have missed it?
你能相信这是我在马路上捡到的吗
Can you believe I found it lying around in the street?
太神了
Amazing
想要的话  下班后就去给你捡假发
If you want to, after work
we could go look for a wig for you
等不及了
I can't wait
假发出动
Wig away
上菜了  章鱼哥
Order up, Squidward
蟹老板
Mr. Krabs
我在这上过了一堆垃圾食品
I've served a lot of junk here
可这头发堡根本不能忍
but a hair patty?
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
什么事  蟹老板
Yes, Mr. Krabs?
你头上戴了什么鬼东西  小子
What in Davy Jones' locker is on your head, son?
我脑袋戴了顶新假发  蟹老板
That's my new wig, Mr. Krabs
摘下来
Well, take it off
头发都掉进蟹黄堡里面了
The hair's getting into the patties
摘下来吗
Take it off?
可我不能摘  蟹老板
But I can't, Mr. Krabs
我的假发给大家带来了快乐
My wig makes everyone so happy
快乐
Happy?
自从我戴上了假发
Ever since I began wearing it
我看到的每个人脸上洋溢着笑容
everyone I see gets a big grin on their face
我想象得到
I can imagine
让我留着假发吧  蟹老板
Please let me keep it, Mr. Krabs
要是假发对你意义这么大  那就留吧
Well, if it means that much to you, you can keep it
但是必须得戴发网
But you've got to wear a hairnet
要是再让我看到蟹黄堡里有头发
And, if I see one more hairy patty
就把你假发丢进垃圾箱
your wig goes in the Dumpster
你在这啊  海绵宝宝
There you are, SpongeBob
准备好要练空手道了吗
Are you ready for karate practice?
看得出来你注意到了我的新假发
I see you've noticed my new wig
很了不起吧
Pretty impressive, huh?
很棒  海绵宝宝
It's great, SpongeBob
真高兴你喜欢
Glad you like it
待会儿见  珊迪
I'll see you later, Sandy
两份蟹黄堡  加帅气当配菜
Two Krabby Patties and a side order of lookin' good
假发不错
Nice wig
喜欢维持造型是吧
Like to keep in style, huh?
确实
You know it
要去见女王了吗  呆子王
Off to meet the queen, Sir Nerd Leroy?
我叫海绵宝宝
The name is SpongeBob
而且我并没要去见皇室成员
and no, I am not meeting royalty
你一定是说我打扮得像皇室成员吧
You must be referring to my regal appearance
谢谢大家说的好话
Thank you all for your kind words
真希望能把这么棒的假发献给大家
I wish I could give you such nice wigs
要不要稍微给你头发剪短一下
How about a little off the top?
你假发大到可以绕着人走一圈了
Yeah, your wig's big enough to go around
这样可不好
This isn't good
大家都开始嫉妒我了
Everyone's getting jealous
章鱼哥  我要藏厨房里
Squidward, I'll be hiding in the kitchen
你有事就进来找我
if you need me
藏好你的丑态  海绵宝宝
Hide your shame, SpongeBob
藏好你的丑态
Hide your shame
大人物唱片
好啊好啊好啊
Well, well, well
尼德针鱼乐队
Ned and the Needlefish
你们被开除了
You're fired
开除
Fired?
为什么
But why?
去问那边那位秃头
Ask Baldy McBaldyson over here
尼德
Ned
太顺利了  兄弟
Good going, dude
我又不是故意没头发的
I can't help not having hair
我们成立这个乐队有且仅有一个原因
We formed this band
it was for one reason and one reason only
就是赚大钱
To make a lot of money
结果你没了头发
And you not having hair
害我们赚不到钱了
is getting in the way of that
我们卖的是唱片  不是假牙牙膏
We are selling records, not denture cream
要么你带着头发回来
Either you come back with hair
要么就别回来了
or don't come back at all
开
大伙儿回去吧
Time to go home, boys
关
就快拖完了
Almost finished
看吧  章鱼哥
See, Squidward?
还很实用哦
It's functional, too
就跟你脑子一样中用
It's about as functional as your brain
谢了  章鱼哥
Thank you, Squidward
我没在夸你
That wasn't a compliment
整个裤头村都在笑你
The entire town is laughing at you
我就不懂了
I don't understand
看看你自己吧
Just look at yourself
你好啊  帅哥
Hello, handsome
海绵宝宝  你脑袋是你以前的两倍大
SpongeBob, your head is twice as large as before
我以前从来没这么高
I've never been tall before
那顶假发染上了寄生虫
That wig is infested with parasites
痒死了
That tickles
看不出来你样子有多可笑吗
Can't you see how ridiculous you look?
我觉得样子挺酷的
I think that it looks cool
就算我把你锁冰库里  你也不懂酷
You wouldn't know cool if I locked you in the freezer
提醒你一下  蟹老板
For your information, Mr. Krabs
章鱼哥以前把我锁冰库里过
Squidward has locked me in the freezer
所以我知道什么叫酷
so I think I know what cool is
以后别戴那顶脏东西来上班了
You stop wearing that nasty thing to work
但是蟹老板
But, Mr. Krabs
不准但是
No "buts"
所以我假发和屁股都不能戴吗
So I can't have a wig or a butt?
[ butt（屁股）与 but（但是）谐音 ]
不对  海绵宝宝
No, SpongeBob
意思就是  不把假发扔掉
It means, until you get rid of that wig
就给我拍屁股走人
get your butt out of here
昨天我一直没机会跟海绵宝宝谈话
I never got a chance to talk to SpongeBob yesterday
我笑得太用力了
I was laughing too hard
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob?
嗨  珊迪
Hi, Sandy
你觉得怎么样
What do you think?
我们得谈谈
We need to talk
礁石影院
正在上映
美发淑女
我为什么得把假发扔掉
Why would I want to get rid of my wig?
看看它给大家带来了多少欢乐
Look how happy it makes everybody
它确实引来了不少注意
Well, it does attract a lot of attention
对啊
I know
大家的目光就是离不开我
People just can't keep their eyes off of me
美发淑女
我的也一样  海绵宝宝
Neither can I, SpongeBob
没错  汤姆
It's true, Tom
这不是我真正的头发
this isn't my real hair
是我偷的
I stole it
借过一下
Pardon me
不好意思
Excuse me
借过一下
Pardon me
假发给我缓冲了
The wig broke my fall
爆米花
Popcorn
你总能站出来挺我
You always come through for me
兄弟  能消停会儿吗
Hey, buddy, do you mind?
看电影讲话很没礼貌
It's very rude to talk during a movie
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob?
你也是  珊迪
You too, Sandy
大家还想看电影呢
People are trying to watch the movie
哪能看得到
Well, they can't
看好  你的破假发把银幕都挡着了
Look, your stupid wig is blocking the whole screen
摘下来  混蛋
Take it off, jerk
前面的
Down in front
假发摘下来
Take the wig off
各位  把注意力放回到电影上吧
People, return your attention to the movie
虽然我的假发迷人又欢欣
I know my wig is glamorous and exciting
但根本就没必要挑起暴动
but there is no need to start a riot
真是个好办法
That's a great idea
来挑起暴动吧
Let's start a riot
抓住他
Get him
就说那部是烂片吧
I told you that movie was terrible
现在明白我说的话了吧  海绵宝宝
Now do you see what I'm saying, SpongeBob?
你说得很对  珊迪
I guess you're right, Sandy
假发给我自己带来了不少快乐
I got so much enjoyment out of the wig myself
我以为它也会给别人快乐
I assumed everyone else did, too
是时候坚强一点了
It's time to be strong
也对
I know
我只想跟你说清楚讲明白
I just want you to know that
尽管我认识你才几天
even though I didn't know you existed a few days ago
我也无法想象没有你的生活
I can't imagine life without you
快一点  海绵宝宝
Hurry up, SpongeBob
无论别人怎么说
No matter what they say
你对我而言  永远都很酷
you'll always be cool to me
我再也不会戴配饰了
I'll never accessorize again
你做出了正确的事  海绵宝宝
You did the right thing, SpongeBob
得上哪去找头发
Where am I going to get some hair?
我的事业毁了
My career is ruined
毁了
Ruined
该不会是
Can it be?
还真是
It is
我的假发
My wig
好
Yes
胜利是我的了
Victory is mine
假发
Wigs
到处都是假发
Wigs, wigs, they're everywhere
他有你的头发
He's got your hair
谢谢
Thank you
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
派大星
Patrick
起码他没戴假发
At least he's not wearing a wig
快看我的新假发
Look at my new wig
大家全都戴着假发
Everyone's wearing wigs
全都戴着
Everyone
我开始觉得自己有点被背叛了
I'm starting to feel a little betrayed
你昨天还取笑过我
You made fun of me yesterday
假发套明明不酷才对吧
I thought powdered wigs were uncool
先前确实不酷
Yeah, they were
但是你看
But look
尼德针鱼乐队
尼德针鱼乐队戴着我的假发
Ned and the Needlefish wearing my wig
原来我抢先酷了一把吗
So I was cool before anyone else?
没错
Yes, you were
但再也没这回事了
But not anymore
再见
See ya
真希望我有顶假发
I wish I had a wig
别难过了  海绵宝宝
Don't be sad, SpongeBob
可以找我借啊
You can borrow one of mine
还之前先洗干净
Just wash it before you return it